♪
IN THE HEART OF AFRICA,
A NEW ERA IS DAWNING.
RWANDA IS ABOUT TO WELCOME HOME
LONG-LOST ROYALTY.
THIS IDYLLIC LANDSCAPE
WAS ONCE THE HUNTING GROUND
FOR MIGHTY PRIDES OF LIONS...
UNTIL A BRUTAL CIVIL WAR
RIPPED THROUGH THE COUNTRY,
KILLING CLOSE
TO TWO MILLION PEOPLE
AND WIPING OUT
ITS MOST ICONIC WILDLIFE.
EVEN THE REGAL LIONS VANISHED.
♪
THE WILDERNESS TURNED
INTO FARMLAND...
AND THE PLAINS FELL SILENT...
UNTIL NOW!
[GROWLING]
♪
[BELLOWING]
[SNARLING]
♪
[ROARING]
AKAGERA, RWANDA'S LARGEST
NATIONAL PARK.
IT'S A TAPESTRY OF HABITATS--
ROLLING MOUNTAINS RISE
FROM SAVANNAHS
AND SPARKLING LAKES
SUPPORT YEAR-ROUND LIFE
ON THE OPEN PLAINS.
FOR THE LAST
TWO AND A HALF DECADES,
THE HERDS OF ANTELOPE HERE
HAVE THRIVED
IN A WORLD FREE
OF BIG PREDATORS.
WITHOUT THE PRESSURE
OF LION PRIDES,
THEY'VE ROAMED THE PLAINS
AND MARSHES UNHINDERED.
THIS IS EDEN FOR ANY HERBIVORE,
BUT THEIR PEACEFUL EXISTENCE
IS ABOUT TO BE SHATTERED.
[VEHICLE APPROACHING]
[HORN HONKS]
SEVEN LIONS HAVE JUST ARRIVED
IN RWANDA!
[CATTLE LOWING]
THEY'VE BEEN HANDPICKED
IN SOUTH AFRICA,
AND THEY'RE TRAVELING
THOUSANDS OF MILES
NORTH OF THEIR HOMELAND.
THEIR DESTINATION: AKAGERA.
THE HOPE IS THAT
THEY WILL FORM A PRIDE...
AND RE-ESTABLISH THE LION
POPULATION IN THIS LAND.
[CLATTERING]
IT'S BEEN A LONG HAUL,
BUT FOR THE KING OF BEASTS,
THIS JOURNEY IS ONLY
JUST BEGINNING.
SUCCESS IN THIS NEW KINGDOM
IS NOT GUARANTEED.
THIS IS THE STARTING GATE...
OF A RACE FOR SURVIVAL.
[TRUCK STARTS]
THE BEST WAY TO LURE A WILD LION
INTO A STRANGE HABITAT
IS THROUGH ITS STOMACH.
[GROWLS]
SHEMA IS HESITANT...
BUT HUNGRY!
[GROWLING]
AT 11 YEARS, SHE'S
THE OLDEST LIONESS HERE.
SHE WAS PICKED
FOR HER EXPERIENCE.
BACK HOME, SHE WAS THE MATRIARCH
OF A STRONG, HEALTHY FAMILY.
BUT THESE OTHER LIONESSES
AREN'T HER SIBLINGS.
THEY'RE STRANGERS
BROUGHT TOGETHER BY FATE.
THE HOPE IS THAT SHEMA CAN
PULL THEM TOGETHER AS A PRIDE.
LIONS ARE THE ONLY CATS
THAT LIVE IN FAMILY GROUPS.
THEIR SUCCESS DEPENDS HEAVILY
ON THEIR SOCIAL STRUCTURE.
A STABLE PRIDE OF LIONS
IS MADE UP OF RELATED FEMALES
WHO HUNT AS A TEAM
AND RAISE THEIR YOUNG TOGETHER.
BEFORE THEY CAN QUALIFY
AS A PRIDE,
THEY WILL NEED TO BOND
AS A SISTERHOOD...
AND ESTABLISH A HIERARCHY.
RIGHT NOW, IT'S JUST HUNGER
THAT UNITES THEM.
NEARBY THE TWO MALES
AWAIT THEIR RELEASE.
♪
INDORO IS A 3-YEAR-OLD MALE...
A YOUNG BRAWLER WHOSE RIGHT EYE
HAS BEEN BLINDED IN A FIGHT.
♪
HIS BROTHER, IZUKA,
LACKS HIS EDGE...
BUT HE'S INDORO'S ONLY ALLY.
TO RE-ESTABLISH A LION COLONY
IN RWANDA,
THE MALES WILL NEED TO BOND
WITH THE FEMALES,
HUNT COOPERATIVELY AND BREED.
FOR THESE TWO YOUNG ROOKIES,
THAT'S A TALL ORDER.
♪
[GROAN]
BINTI IS THE LAST TO EXIT.
[GROWLING]
STILL WEARING THE DARK SPOTS
OF CHILDHOOD,
SHE IS THE YOUNGEST
OF THE LIONESSES
AND THE MOST NERVOUS.
AT ONLY 18 MONTHS OLD,
SHE'S THE LOWEST RANKING MEMBER.
[SNARLING]
TO SURVIVE,
SHE'LL NEED THE SUPPORT
OF THE OLDER FEMALES,
BOTH AS HUNTERS
AND AS TEACHERS.
IN A PRIDE BOUND BY BLOOD,
THESE LIONESSES WOULD EACH
KNOW THEIR ROLE
AND THEIR PLACE.
[SNARLING]
BUT THIS RAGTAG BUNCH
ARE GOING TO HAVE TO
WORK THAT OUT FROM SCRATCH.
♪
LIONS ARE NOCTURNAL,
AND AS THE SUN SETS,
THEY FEEL CONFIDENT ENOUGH
TO VENTURE INTO THE UNKNOWN.
[ANIMALS HOWLING]
SHEMA WAS THE FIRST
OUT OF THE GATE,
AND NOW SHE'S FIRST TO LEAVE
THE RELEASE SITE.
THE LOOSE-KNIT SISTERHOOD
FOLLOWS.
IT'S A GOOD START.
SHEMA'S MATURITY MIGHT JUST HOLD
THIS BAND OF STRANGERS TOGETHER.
THE BROTHERS ARE ALSO
ON THE MOVE,
BUT THEY'RE DISORIENTED.
THEY'RE HEADING NORTH,
AWAY FROM THE FEMALES.
IT'S THE WRONG MOVE.
[ANIMAL BARKING]
THEY WERE EARMARKED
AS THE FUTURE KINGS OF AKAGERA,
BUT THEY'VE GOT A LOT TO LEARN.
NOTORIOUSLY LAZY, MALE LIONS
RELY ON THE PRIDE LIONESSES
TO NAVIGATE...
AND BRING HOME THE BACON.
TOTALLY LACKING
SURVIVAL SKILLS,
THESE TWO AREN'T READY
TO MAKE IT OUT HERE ALONE.
[HYENA WHOOPING]
SHEMA FOLLOWS
HER INSTINCTS SOUTH.
SHE'S HEADING TOWARDS
HER FORMER HOMELAND
AT THE TIP OF AFRICA.
[CHATTERING]
SHE'S ABOUT TO HAVE HER
FIRST BRUSH WITH THE LOCALS.
A GANG OF HYENAS
RULES THIS TURF.
[YIPPING]
LIKE MOST OF THE LOCAL WILDLIFE,
THESE YOUNG MOBSTERS HAVE NEVER
SEEN A LION BEFORE.
THEIR AMAZEMENT IS CLEAR--
THEY HAVE NO IDEA
THAT SHEMA IS A RIVAL.
[YIPPING]
[GROWLS]
BUT SHEMA HAS A LIFETIME
OF HYENA CONTEMPT.
[YIPPING]
THE AGE-OLD RIVALRY
RUNS DEEP IN HER VEINS.
SHE PAWS THE GROUND, DEPOSITING
A TERRITORIAL SCENT MARK
FROM GLANDS BETWEEN HER TOES.
AS A LONE LIONESS,
THE GANG OF HYENAS
COULD EASILY TAKE HER ON.
FOR NOW, THEIR IGNORANCE
IS HER ONLY ALLY.
[YIPPING AND SHRIEKING]
FIVE MILES NORTH,
THE BROTHERS ARE STILL
ON THEIR MISGUIDED JOURNEY.
YOUNG MALES USUALLY
HAVE TO FIGHT FOR TERRITORY
WHEN THEY COME OF AGE...
BUT THESE LUCKY UPSTARTS
HAVE BEEN OFFERED A NEW EMPIRE
AT NO COST.
AND THIS KINGDOM
LOOKS PROMISING.
25 YEARS WITHOUT LIONS
HAVE ALLOWED LARGE HERDS
OF IMPALA TO THRIVE,
UNCHECKED AND UNSUSPECTING.
[GRUMBLING]
LIKE DEER IN THE HEADLIGHTS,
THE USUALLY SKITTISH PREY
ARE CLUELESS
ABOUT "PREDATOR PROTOCOL."
LUCKY FOR THEM, THE LIONS
SEEM EQUALLY CONFUSED.
♪
THE BROTHERS HAVE THE WORLD
AT THEIR FEET...
BUT THEY NEED TO GET A GRIP!
♪
IT'S DAY TWO
IN AKAGERA, RWANDA.
WITH SHEMA AT THE HELM,
THE FIVE LIONESSES
HAVE REACHED THE HIGH PEAKS
IN THE SOUTH OF THE PARK.
IT'S THE END OF THE DRY SEASON
AND A RECENT WILDFIRE
HAS SWEPT THROUGH,
SCORCHING THE LANDSCAPE
AND EXPOSING ROCKY GROUND.
[URINATING]
THIS IS STRANGE NEW TERRAIN
FOR THE LIONESSES.
THE PLAINS OF THEIR HOMELAND
WERE FLAT, GRASSY SAVANNAHS...
WITH NO HIGH VANTAGE POINTS.
[GROANS]
FOR THE FIRST TIME
IN THEIR LIVES
THEY CAN LOOK OUT
INTO THE DISTANCE...
DOWN VALLEYS, PAST LAKES
AND ACROSS A VAST WILDERNESS.
[ZEBRA BRAYING]
IT MAY BE ALIEN TERRITORY,
BUT THE TRUE BOUNTY
OF THEIR NEW KINGDOM
IS SUDDENLY CLEAR.
♪
SHEMA LEADS
THE LIONESSES ONWARD,
SEARCHING FOR NEW
HUNTING GROUNDS.
♪
AS THE PLAINS OPEN UP
IN FRONT OF HER, IT'S CLEAR--
THEY'VE ARRIVED!
♪
THE SPRAWLING MARSHLANDS
ARE AN OASIS
FOR ALL THE PARK'S WILDLIFE.
♪
TWO GENERATIONS OF GRAZERS
HAVE FROLICKED HERE...
WITHOUT THREAT...
BUT ALL THAT'S
ABOUT TO CHANGE.
THE LIONS ARE BACK IN TOWN.
THE COOL WATER
IS A WELCOME DRINK
AFTER THE BURNED-OUT MOUNTAINS.
[ZEBRA BRAYING]
THERE'S LUSH GRASSLAND
AS FAR AS THE EYE CAN SEE.
THE PREY ARE FAT FROM GRAZING...
AND BLISSFULLY UNAWARE
OF THE DANGER IN THEIR MIDST.
A FAMILY OF WARTHOGS APPROACHES,
INTRIGUED BY
THEIR NEW NEIGHBORS.
[GRUNTING]
IN THEIR SHORT LIFESPAN, THEY'VE
NEVER SEEN SUCH A BEAST.
[GRUNTING]
[SNIFFING]
[BARKING]
THE ELDERS OF THE BABOON TROOP
RAISE THE ALARM.
THEY'VE BEEN AROUND
MUCH LONGER,
AND A DISTANT MEMORY
REARS ITS HEAD.
[SHRIEKING]
THIS IS NOW LION COUNTRY!
AND SHEMA'S GOING TO PROVE IT.
[BABOONS SQUAWKING]
AT 300 POUNDS, A FULL-GROWN TOPI
WOULD MAKE A GOOD MEAL
FOR FIVE LIONESSES.
IT LOOKS LIKE EASY PICKINGS...
BUT LOOKS CAN BE DECEIVING.
TOPI ARE THE FASTEST ANTELOPE
IN AKAGERA.
THEY CAN REACH SPEEDS
OF UP TO 50 MILES PER HOUR--
FASTER THAN ANY PREY
THEY HUNTED BACK HOME.
IT WILL TAKE SKILL AND STRATEGY
TO BRING ONE DOWN.
[SNORTS]
♪
THE TOPI IS SURROUNDED,
BUT HIS FLIGHT INSTINCT
HASN'T KICKED IN.
♪
BINTI BREAKS EARLY,
BLOWING SHEMA'S COVER.
♪
THE TOPI ESCAPES
WITHOUT BREAKING A SWEAT.
IT'S A BIG FAIL.
THEY HAVE A UNIQUE OPPORTUNITY
TO PICK OFF PREY OBLIVIOUS
TO DANGER...
BUT UNTIL THEY FORM BONDS
AND HUNT COOPERATIVELY,
THE LIONESSES WILL GO HUNGRY.
ACROSS THE LAKE,
THE BROTHERS HAVE MADE IT
DOWN FROM THE NORTH.
THEY'RE APPROACHING THE MARSHES
FROM THE OPPOSITE SIDE.
BUT THIS IS HIPPO COUNTRY!
[GRUNTING]
THESE 3-TON BEASTS
RULE THE WATERWAYS,
AND THEY DON'T WELCOME VISITORS.
A TERRITORIAL BULL WILL TAKE ON
ANY INTERLOPER...
AND THERE'S A BODY COUNT
TO PROVE IT.
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
FOR HUNGRY SCAVENGERS,
A HIPPO CARCASS IS A FEAST
FIT FOR A KING...
BUT THERE'S NO SUCH THING
AS A FREE MEAL.
THIS CANTANKEROUS CREATURE
IS THE DEADLIEST VEGETARIAN
ON THE PLANET.
[SNORTS]
HE'S 40 YEARS OLD...
AND HE REMEMBERS THE SMELL
OF A DANGEROUS PREDATOR.
[BELLOWS]
INDORO HAS ALSO PICKED UP
ON A SCENT.
IT'S THE STENCH
OF ROTTING FLESH...
AND HE'S HUNGRY.
BUT TO GET TO THIS FEAST,
HE'LL NEED TO BRAVE THE HIPPO
AND NEGOTIATE
THE MARSHY TERRAIN.
[GROANING]
HIS HUNTING SKILLS
ARE SORELY LACKING,
AND HE WON'T TURN HIS NOSE UP
AT A SCAVENGED MEAL.
BUT THE STICKY MUD
IS A WHOLE NEW CHALLENGE.
ALL THAT STANDS BETWEEN INDORO
AND HIS FEAST
IS TWO INCHES
OF TOUGH HIPPO HIDE.
[GROANS]
BUT THE MUD TURNS
THE BIG CAT SKITTISH.
INDORO BACKS UP, DEFEATED.
IZUKA TRIES NEXT, BUT HE FACES
THE SAME CONUNDRUM.
♪
THEY'RE TOO VULNERABLE
IN THIS UNFAMILIAR MARSH.
THE BOYS WILL GO HUNGRY
FOR ANOTHER NIGHT.
[GRUNTING]
THEIR BEST BET
IS TO GO BACK TO BASICS--
FIND THE FEMALES
AND LET THEM DO THE HUNTING.
[ROARING]
THE BROTHERS CALL INTO THE NIGHT
TO ADVERTISE THEIR PRESENCE.
[ROAR]
THEIR ROARS ECHO FOR MILES.
[ROARING]
IT'S A SOUND THAT HASN'T BEEN
HEARD IN RWANDA FOR 25 YEARS.
[ROARING]
THREE MILES AWAY...
SHEMA REPLIES.
[ROARING]
[DISTANT ROARING]
THROUGHOUT THE NIGHT
THEY CALL TO EACH OTHER...
AND IN THE MORNING, SHEMA
SETS OFF TO HEED THEIR ROARS.
THIS TIME SHE TRAVELS ALONE.
SHE'S IN HEAT, AND THERE'S
ONLY ONE DESTINATION.
♪
[PURRING]
SHEMA AND INDORO RUB HEADS.
IT'S A POSITIVE GREETING
AND AN IMPORTANT MOMENT.
FOR SHEMA
IT COULD MEAN A MATE...
AND FOR THE MALES,
A USEFUL HUNTER.
♪
AS MATRIARCH OF HER OLD PRIDE,
SHEMA WOULD HAVE PROVIDED
FOR THE YOUNG MALES.
AND TRUE TO FORM,
NOW SHE WASTES NO TIME
IN SETTING OFF TO HUNT.
ONCE AGAIN, SHE HAS NO BACKUP,
BUT SHE'S HUNGRY ENOUGH
FOR A SOLO ATTEMPT.
A YOUNG WATERBUCK
IS A TANTALIZING MEAL.
BUT IN BROAD DAYLIGHT THE ODDS
ARE STACKED AGAINST THE HUNTER.
♪
OUT IN THE OPEN, SHEMA'S GOT
NO COVER TO MASK HER INTENTIONS.
♪
BUT THE INNOCENT WATERBUCK
DOESN'T RECOGNIZE
THE SMELL OF DANGER.
IT DOESN'T RUN.
TO SHEMA, THAT'S CONFUSING.
♪
SHE BACKS UP...
BUT THEN CHANGES HER MIND.
IT'S TOO GOOD A CHANCE
TO PASS UP.
♪
[WATERBUCK WAILING]
SHEMA HAS DONE IT!
SHE'S THE FIRST LION TO MAKE
A KILL IN RWANDA IN 25 YEARS!
IT PROVES SHE CAN SURVIVE HERE,
EVEN ON HER OWN.
MORE SIGNIFICANTLY, SHE'S PROVEN
HERSELF TO A POTENTIAL MATE.
HER KILL WILL FEED
THREE HUNGRY BELLIES
AND SOLIDIFY HER ALLIANCE
WITH THE MALES.
[SNARLING]
THE BROTHERS ARE STARVING...
BUT IT'S NO FREE FOR ALL.
FEEDING IS ALL ABOUT HIERARCHY,
AND IT'S INDORO
WHO TAKES HIS PLACE
AT THE TOP OF THIS FOOD CHAIN.
HIS ACTIONS CONFIRM
THAT HE'S THE ALPHA MALE.
IZUKA MUST NEGOTIATE
HIS PLACE AT THE MEAL.
[SNARLING]
[GRUMBLING]
SHEMA, THE BREADWINNER,
MUST WAIT.
BUT HER CONTRIBUTION
WON'T GO UNNOTICED.
[GRUMBLING]
FOR INDORO, AN ALLEGIANCE WITH
A STRONG HUNTRESS IS ESSENTIAL.
HE CAN'T RELY ON HIS BROTHER
FOR FOOD;
THEIR SIBLING BOND
IS ONLY USEFUL
WHEN FIGHTING RIVAL MALES.
SHEMA HAS PROVEN HERSELF
AS A GOOD PROVIDER,
AND SHE'S STILL IN HEAT.
TO INDORO, SHE'S IRRESISTIBLE.
HIS INSTINCTS DRIVE HIM TO FORM
A PRIDE AND SIRE OFFSPRING.
SHEMA IS THE KEY.
♪
AT DAYBREAK,
INDORO TAKES HIS NEW QUEEN
TO THE TOP OF THE HILLS,
LEAVING IZUKA
TO FEND FOR HIMSELF.
HIGH ABOVE THEIR NEW KINGDOM
THEY FORGE A FUTURE GENERATION
FOR RWANDA'S LION POPULATION.
♪
OVER THE NEXT FEW DAYS
THEY WILL BE INSEPARABLE,
MATING UP TO 100 TIMES PER DAY.
♪
[GROWLING]
[ELEPHANT TRUMPETING]
FOUR DAYS LATER, THE COURTING
COUPLE RETURN TO THE PLAINS.
THEY HAVE COMPANY.
THE OTHER LIONESSES
HAVE ARRIVED.
INDORO REUNITES
WITH HIS BROTHER.
HE'S FULL OF VIGOR AND SHOWING
THE CONFIDENCE OF AN ALPHA MALE.
TOGETHER THE BROTHERS RALLY
TO MEET THEIR VISITORS.
♪
FOR THE VERY FIRST TIME...
ALL SEVEN LIONS COME TOGETHER
ON THEIR NEW TURF.
THIS IS THE KEY
TO THEIR SUCCESS IN RWANDA--
FIVE STRONG LIONESSES,
WITH A DOMINANT MALE AS MATE
AND GUARDIAN.
BUT THEY STILL NEED TO BOND.
[GROWLING]
THEY WON'T BE A PRIDE
UNTIL THEY HUNT AS A TEAM...
AND PRODUCE CUBS OF THEIR OWN.
TO THESE LIONESSES,
A DOMINANT MALE IS HOT PROPERTY.
SUDDENLY SHEMA MUST FIGHT
FOR HER PLACE IN THIS HIERARCHY.
SHE MOUNTS A YOUNG FEMALE, KAZI,
IN A DISPLAY THAT SHOWS
SHE'S THE TOP CAT.
[PURRING]
[SNARLING]
IT MIGHT NOT BE ENOUGH.
KAZI IS IN HEAT, TOO,
AND INDORO WILL TAKE
EVERY OPPORTUNITY
TO PASS ON HIS GENES.
BARBS ON HIS PENIS
TRIGGER HER OVULATION...
[GROWLING]
BUT THE PAIN ALSO TRIGGERS
A HOSTILE REACTION.
[GROWLING]
INDORO IS SHOWING
ALL THE HALLMARKS
OF A DOMINANT MALE...
THROWING HIS WEIGHT AROUND
AND MATING REPEATEDLY.
THIS FREQUENT COUPLING
MAXIMIZES HIS CHANCES
OF SIRING A NEW GENERATION.
ONLY ONE IN THREE ATTEMPTS
IS SUCCESSFUL.
[GROWLING]
INDORO HAS COME OF AGE...
AND HE'S FORGING
THE PRIDE DYNAMICS.
BUT JUST AS THE GROUP
COMES TOGETHER,
SOMETHING CHANGES.
♪
SHEMA SETS OFF ALONE...
LEAVING THE LION POLITICS
TO THE OTHERS.
A DEEP INSTINCT
IS CALLING HER AWAY.
SURVIVAL ON HER OWN IS RISKY...
BUT OF THE SEVEN, ONLY SHEMA
HAS PROVEN HERSELF AS A HUNTER.
HER DEPARTURE COULD SPELL
DISASTER FOR THEM ALL.
♪
AS THE DOMINANT MALE,
INDORO GETS THE FIRST SHOT
AT ALL THE FEMALES.
IT'S NOT NEGOTIABLE.
[GROWLS]
BUT WHEN HE'S NOT AROUND,
IZUKA SNEAKS AWAY WITH KAZI.
[PURRING]
IT'S A RARE OPPORTUNITY
FOR A QUICK FLING--
HE'LL ONLY EVER GET THIS CHANCE
WHEN HIS BROTHER LOSES STAMINA.
[PURRING]
[GROWLING]
[ROARING]
♪
IT'S BEEN A WEEK SINCE SHEMA
LEFT THE REST OF THE PRIDE.
TEN MILES NORTH OF THE MARSH,
SHE'S FOUND THE PERFECT HABITAT
TO STRIKE OUT ON HER OWN.
IT'S A HUNTER'S PARADISE--
FLAT GRASSY PLAINS
AND AN ABUNDANCE OF PREY.
♪
[SNORTS]
SHE SOUGHT IT OUT FOR A REASON--
THE SAME REASON
SHE SET OUT ON HER OWN.
♪
SHE'S NO LONGER HUNTING
FOR HER OWN SURVIVAL.
SHE'S CARRYING
THE FUTURE HEIRS OF AKAGERA.
AND THAT'S AN HONOR
SHE'LL KILL FOR.
THE IMPALA OF AKAGERA
ARE LARGER AND STRONGER THAN
THOSE SHEMA HUNTED BACK HOME.
THEIR HORNS TOWER OVER THEM
LIKE GREAT SPEARS.
♪
SHEMA IS UNDAUNTED.
SHE SITS TIGHT.
AS A LONER, HER ONLY OPTION
IS AMBUSH.
♪
[IMPALA SCREAMING]
SHEMA'S JAWS CLAMP DOWN
ON THE IMPALA'S WINDPIPE,
SUFFOCATING HIM.
SHE DRAGS HER PREY TO THE SHADE.
HIS BROKEN HIND LEG
SEALS HIS FATE.
[GROANING]
THE IMPALA ARE UNSURE
HOW TO REACT.
[SNORTS]
THEY'VE NEVER WITNESSED
A KILL BEFORE.
SHEMA'S ALSO IN OVER HER HEAD.
SHE UNDERESTIMATED
THE STRENGTH OF THIS RAM.
[GROANING]
ON THREE LEGS HE'S AT HER MERCY,
BUT SHE MUST STAY CLEAR
OF HIS LETHAL HORNS.
SHEMA DELIVERS
HER KISS OF DEATH.
SHE NO LONGER NEEDS
TO SHARE HER KILLS,
BUT HUNTING ON HER OWN IS RISKY,
AND IT'S COME
AT A VERY HIGH PRICE.
[SNORTS]
ONE SPEAR-SHARP HORN
HAS FOUND ITS MARK
AND PUNCTURED HER LEG.
THE WOUND IS SMALL BUT DEEP,
AND HER MUSCLES ARE STILL
HURTING FROM THE STRUGGLE.
HER BELLY'S FULL,
BUT SHE'S BARELY ABLE TO WALK.
ALONE AND UNABLE TO HUNT,
SHE'LL STARVE TO DEATH.
SHEMA'S FUTURE LOOKS BLEAK.
[THUNDER]
A FAMILIAR RUMBLE ECHOES
THROUGH THE ROLLING HILLS
AND GRASSY PLAINS.
[THUNDER]
IT'S THE START
OF THE RAINY SEASON.
IN RWANDA THE HEAVY RAINS
LAST SEVERAL MONTHS--
FLOODING THE PLAINS
AND CHANGING THE LANDSCAPE.
[THUNDER]
FOR THE SEVEN LIONS
OF AKAGERA NATIONAL PARK,
THIS IS A MISERABLE TIME.
CATS NOTORIOUSLY HATE WATER.
BACK HOME, THE RAINY SEASON
WAS DEFINED BY A FEW BIG STORMS.
[THUNDER]
THIS INCESSANT DOWNPOUR
IS NOT WHAT THEY SIGNED UP FOR.
[BIRDS SINGING]
THE RAINS HAVE COME AND GONE,
AND THE LUSH PLAINS ARE RESTORED
TO AN EDEN ONCE MORE.
THE LIONS HAVE SURVIVED THE WET
AND ESTABLISHED THEIR HOME
IN THIS NEW KINGDOM.
SHEMA HAS NOT RETURNED...
BUT NEW BONDS ARE FORMING
BETWEEN THE REMAINING
FOUR LIONESSES.
KAZI HAS TAKEN BINTI
UNDER HER WING...
AND THE DYNAMICS OF A PRIDE
ARE STARTING TO SHOW.
BUT THERE'S STILL ONE CRITICAL
MILESTONE ON THEIR HORIZON--
TO QUALIFY AS A TRUE PRIDE,
THEY NEED TO HUNT
AS A COORDINATED TEAM.
[GRUNTING]
IN A MATERNAL PRIDE,
EACH LION LEARNS
A SPECIALIZED HUNTING ROLE
FROM BIRTH.
THEY'RE EITHER A WING,
WHO STALKS AND ENCIRCLES PREY,
OR A CENTER,
WHO LIES IN AMBUSH TO TRAP IT.
[BUFFALO GRUNTING]
[GROWLING]
[GRUNTING]
THESE SIX LIONS
KNOW THEIR ROLES.
THEY JUST CAN'T FIGURE OUT
HOW TO PULL TOGETHER AS A TEAM.
[GRUMBLING]
BACK HOME, BUFFALO WAS A STAPLE
ON THEIR MENU...
BUT UNTIL THEY CAN SYNCHRONIZE
THEIR HUNTING STRATEGY,
THEY'LL BE FORCED TO EAT
HUMBLE PIE.
♪
ACROSS THE MARSH, SHEMA
IS STILL KEEPING HER DISTANCE.
♪
IT'S BEEN TOUGH,
BUT SHE'S A SURVIVOR...
AND NOW HER DAYS OF SOLITUDE
ARE OVER.
SHE'S A SINGLE MOM
TO THREE HEALTHY CUBS.
♪
GOING SOLO WAS A RISK, BUT SHE
NEEDED TO FIND A SAFE HIDEOUT
TO GIVE BIRTH TO HER OFFSPRING.
AS FRAGILE NEWBORNS,
SHE COULDN'T INTRODUCE THEM
INTO AN UNRULY GROUP
OF NON-RELATED LIONS.
♪
RIGHT NOW, THEIR SURVIVAL
DEPENDS ENTIRELY ON HER.
SHE MUST KEEP HER STRENGTH UP
TO FULFILL HER MATERNAL ROLES.
♪
SHE NEEDS TO HUNT...
AND THAT MEANS LEAVING
HER BABIES ALONE.
♪
[HYENAS WHOOPING]
[HYENA YIPPING]
SHEMA WAITS FOR NIGHTFALL
FOR THE BEST CHANCE TO KILL.
HUNTING ON HER OWN,
SHE HAS LIMITED OPTIONS.
SHE NEEDS TO AMBUSH...
AND SHE CAN'T PIT HERSELF
AGAINST ANYTHING TOO BIG.
STAKING OUT A WARTHOG BURROW
IS A GOOD PLAN.
SHEMA SITS UPWIND...
MAKING THE PIGS BOLT!
[GRUNTING AND SQUEALING]
[WARTHOG SQUEALING]
SHE'S RIGHT ON TARGET.
[SQUEALING]
SHE GOES FOR THE THROAT,
BUT THIS TIME HER PREY
HAS LETHAL TUSKS IN FRONT.
ONE GOOD HEAD-BUTT
COULD MAIM HER.
BACK IN THEIR DEN, SHEMA'S CUBS
AWAIT THEIR FIRST SOLID MEAL.
[FLIES BUZZING]
THERE ARE MIXED REACTIONS--
ONE CUB DIGS IN
WHILE ANOTHER SEEMS DAUNTED.
[PURRING]
FOR SOME, MOTHER'S MILK
IS STILL THE MEAL OF CHOICE.
IN RWANDA, SHEMA MEANS "PRIDE,"
AND FOR THIS PROUD LIONESS,
HER THREE CUBS
ARE THE FIRST GENERATION
OF A NEW BLOODLINE IN AKAGERA.
SOON THEY WILL JOIN FORCES
WITH THE OTHERS...
AND CEMENT THE FOUNDATIONS
OF A TRUE MATERNAL LION PRIDE,
WITH INDORO AS THEIR KING.
SHEMA HAS PLAYED HER ROLE
AND MADE HER MARK
IN RWANDA'S HISTORY.
[PURRING]
NOT FAR FROM SHEMA'S NURSERY,
THE REST OF THE LIONS
ARE SET FOR THEIR OWN VICTORY.
♪
HUNGER HAS SPED UP
THEIR LEARNING CURVE...
AND THEY'RE FINALLY WORKING
AS A UNIT.
♪
THE IMPALA ARE STILL
LARGELY IGNORANT
OF THE PREDATORS IN THEIR MIDST.
THEY HAVEN'T LEARNED MUCH
FROM THEIR MISTAKES.
THE FLEDGLING PRIDE
HAS THEM SURROUNDED.
KAZI IS AN EXPERT WING.
SHE COMES IN
FROM THE BLIND SIDE.
THE BROTHERS TAKE
THE OPPOSITE FLANK.
♪
[GROANING]
THE IMPALA NEVER STOOD A CHANCE.
TEAMWORK INCREASES
THE SUCCESS RATE.
[SNORTING]
WHEN THERE'S A STRATEGY,
EVEN AN AMATEUR CAN MAKE A KILL.
♪
[WAILING]
BINTI TAKES DOWN
A YOUNG WATERBUCK.
IT'S HER FIRST SOLO KILL.
UNDER KAZI'S GUIDANCE,
SHE'S FINALLY COME OF AGE.
BUT SHE'S STILL
THE LOWEST RANKING FEMALE...
AND HER GLORY DOESN'T LAST LONG.
THE MALES LAY CLAIM
TO HER PRIZE.
THE LEADERS ALWAYS EAT FIRST.
THIS IS LION LAW.
[GRUMBLING]
[GROWLS]
TO THEM, THE LAST DYING BLEATS
OF THE WATERBUCK
ARE NOTHING MORE
THAN THE DINNER BELL.
THE LIONS' INSTINCTS
ARE TAKING OVER.
THE FEMALES ARE HUNTING
SUCCESSFULLY.
THE MALES HAVE STEPPED UP
TO THE PLATE,
ESTABLISHED A HIERARCHY
AND PRODUCED CUBS.
♪
THEY ARE A PRIDE...AT LAST!
ONE YEAR AGO, SEVEN LIONS
ARRIVED IN RWANDA.
STRANGERS TO EACH OTHER,
THEY WEATHERED THE STORMS...
FORGED RELATIONSHIPS...
AND SIRED CUBS.
A YEAR AGO,
THIS EDEN WAS INCOMPLETE...
MISSING A CRUCIAL LINK
IN ITS DELICATE ECOSYSTEM...
ITS MOST ICONIC SPECIES EXTINCT,
ALMOST FORGOTTEN.
AND THEN THEY ARRIVED...
A RAGTAG BUNCH MADE UP
OF MISFITS AND LONERS.
OUT OF THEIR DEPTH
AND LOST IN THE WILDERNESS,
THEY ROSE TO THEIR CHALLENGES
AND MASTERED THEIR NEW KINGDOM.
[SCREAMING]
♪
THESE MAGNIFICENT SEVEN,
SYMBOLS OF BALANCE,
POWER AND COURAGE,
HAVE COMPLETED
THE CIRCLE OF LIFE...
AND RESTORED THE PRIDE
OF A NATION.
♪